<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title> - philosophy</title>
    <subtitle>Viraj Sazzala&#x27;s personal website</subtitle>
    <link href="https://virajsazzala.xyz/tags/philosophy/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://virajsazzala.xyz"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2024-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://virajsazzala.xyz/tags/philosophy/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Symphony of Sobriety</title>
        <published>2024-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://virajsazzala.xyz/blog/symphony-of-sobriety/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://virajsazzala.xyz/blog/symphony-of-sobriety/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We’ve all sort of melded into a collective consiousness, a hive mind, without really noticing we’re losing our individuality. It’s like we’re in a trance, believing whatever the majority says and ignoring anyone who’s different. We’re obsessed with success, power, and money, thinking that’s what life’s about. We listen to the rich, do what they say, and sometimes even hurt others just to be like them. But deep down, we’re lost, not sure why we’re here or what we’re supposed to do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone once said life is just one long struggle, and it’s up to us to pick how we want to suffer. So why do so many people choose the hardest path, living in misery instead of finding a way out? Somehow, many of us end up in a kind of self-made hell, stuck in suffering that we’ve chosen. It’s like we’re trapped in a dark place, thinking this is just how life is meant to be. It’s like plunging into the depths of hell, isn’t it? We find ourselves in this grim landscape of suffering, we’re shackled by our own choices, bound by chains of self-doubt and fear But why? Why pick the worst kind of pain and stick with it? There’s this weird idea that if you try to break free from the misery, you’re weak or cowardly. But maybe it’s the other way around. Maybe it takes real strength to say, “I’m done with this,” and try to find a way out. It’s like following the crowd right into the flames, thinking it’s the right thing to do, when maybe the real truth lies in escaping those flames altogether. Just because everyone thinks something’s right doesn’t mean it actually is. Sometimes, the truth is found in the quiet voices of those who don’t fit in.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Endless Perspectives</title>
        <published>2023-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://virajsazzala.xyz/blog/endless-perspectives/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://virajsazzala.xyz/blog/endless-perspectives/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;virajsazzala.xyz&#x2F;blog&#x2F;endless-perspectives&#x2F;#overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world teeming with billions, the notion that each person sees just one version of you doesn’t quite fit, does it? Think about your day: encounters with countless individuals, from the bus driver, to the friends you cherish, each painting a different picture of who they believe you are. It’s as if everyone carries their own unique pair of glasses, shaping their distinct viewpoint of you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a tendency to tune into these perceptions, to align ourselves with how others see us. We might tweak our personalities, adjust our actions, all to harmonize with the multifaceted reflections of ourselves mirrored in the opinions of others. But in this intricate dance, it’s easy to lose sight of our authentic selves, our true essence, buried beneath the amalgamation of varied perceptions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;let-s-understand-this&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;virajsazzala.xyz&#x2F;blog&#x2F;endless-perspectives&#x2F;#divedeeper&quot;&gt;Let’s understand this&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Let’s simplify this&lt;&#x2F;b&gt;: If ‘x’ represents the number of people acquainted with your existence, the sum total of how people see you amounts to ‘x’ plus one—factoring in your own perception of yourself. You might not be able to alter all those ‘x’ different views others have of you, but the most crucial one, the one you have the power to change, is your own.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As time ticks on, you encounter more individuals, each contributing to the expanding ‘x,’ and subsequently, a growing pile of diverse perspectives. The weight of trying to match up to these myriad viewpoints can become burdensome. Yet, if you focus on refining your own viewpoint, that load becomes remarkably lighter.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;existing-works&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;virajsazzala.xyz&#x2F;blog&#x2F;endless-perspectives&#x2F;#exisitingworks&quot;&gt;Existing works&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this tapestry of perceptions, there’s a beautiful thought experiment called the “Looking Glass Self” theory by &lt;em&gt;Charles Cooley&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Cooley suggests that our self-concept is a mosaic fashioned from the reflections of others’ opinions—a notion echoed by modern psychological research.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work of &lt;em&gt;Carl Rogers&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, for instance, underscores how our self-concept is sculpted by the feedback and evaluations received from our social interactions. Studies in social psychology, such as those delving into self-perception theory by &lt;em&gt;Daryl Bem&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and social comparison theory by &lt;em&gt;Henri Tajfel&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Leon Festinger&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, consistently reinforce the idea that external feedback significantly shapes our self-perception.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These theories and empirical studies point to the influence of tons external perspectives on our self-concept, emphasizing the significance of nurturing one’s own viewpoint amidst the kaleidoscope of perceptions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these endless viewpoints, while the number of external views may increase, the true compass for personal growth and self-understanding remains your own view of yourself. It’s this singular perspective that should guide your journey toward self-actualization.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, even today, we can see how much people crave attention through Instagram stories, reels, TikToks, and more. Everyday individuals share every aspect of their lives, often forgetting to experience these moments fully. A single negative comment on their post or story can sour their entire day. There’s an unspoken expectation for positive validation, and if not received, people go to great lengths to change that perception.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;virajsazzala.xyz&#x2F;blog&#x2F;endless-perspectives&#x2F;#conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, don’t get stuck in this bubble, get out, be better, happier. Read because you want to, not because you see a book on someone’s story. Study because you are interested, not because others are doing it. Listen to music because you love it, not because some artist is popular. Love because you felt it, not because you need it. Smile because it comes on your face, not because you have to pose for a picture. Live your life, in a peaceful way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, &lt;u&gt;it might be lonely living this way, but it’ll be peaceful and pretty&lt;&#x2F;u&gt;. Choose authenticity over conformity, genuine experiences over curated moments, and your own passions over societal expectations. Embrace the beauty of living for yourself, not for the perceptions of others.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
